<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<scientific-paper
    xmlns="http://www.ftn.uns.ac.rs/scientific-paper"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ftn.uns.ac.rs/scientific-paper"
    received="2016-12-21" revised="2016-04-15" accepted="2016-04-15">
    
    <header>
        <title>Document phenomenology: a framework for holistic analysis</title>
        
        <authors>
            <author>
                <first-name>Tim</first-name>
                <last-name>Gorichanaz</last-name>
                
                <institution>
                    <name>Drexel University</name>
                    <location>
                        <city>Philadelphia </city>
                        <state>Pennsylvania </state>
                        <country>USA </country>
                    </location>
                </institution>
            </author>
            
            <author>
                <first-name>Kiersten</first-name>
                <middle-name> F. </middle-name>
                <last-name>Latham</last-name>
                
                <institution>
                    <name>Kent State University</name>
                    <location>
                        <city>Kent </city>
                        <state>Ohio</state>
                        <country>USA </country>
                    </location>
                </institution>
            </author>
        </authors>
    </header>
    
    <abstract>
        <purpose>
            – The purpose of this paper is to advance document ontology and epistemology by
            proposing a framework for analysing documents from multiple perspectives of research and practice.
            Design/methodology/approach – Understanding is positioned as an epistemic aim of documents
        </purpose>
        
        <keywords>
            Phenomenology, Document analysis, Document experience, Document handling,
            Document systems, Properties of documentary practice
        </keywords>
        
        <paper-type>Conceptual paper</paper-type>  
    </abstract>
    
    <sections>
        <section heading="Introduction">
            <paragraph>
                Do documents exist? Or, perhaps more to the point: how do documents exist?
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
                Questions about existence are, of course, not unique to documents, as evidenced by
                the sprawling literature in ontological philosophy. Yet, as Heidegger (1927/2010)
                pointed out, most of this inquiry assumes existence as a fait accompli and is more
                interested in questions regarding, for instance, classification. In Heidegger’s terms,
                traditional ontology asks questions about beings, not about being.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
                With documents, assuming existence as self-evident – failing to ask about being –
                raises a host of issues. If a document is taken to be anything that furnishes evidence or
                proof of something <italic>(Buckland, 1997) </italic>, how is it that objects become documents? And
                why do some things become documents while others do not? How can we account for,
                to give Meyriat’s (1981) example, Napoleon’s letters, which furnished one sort of proof
            </paragraph>
        </section>
        
        <section heading="What is holistic analysis?">
            <paragraph>
                Analysis is a detailed examination of the elements or structure of something. It is a way
                to break something into its parts to make the appreciation of it more manageable. At its
                best, analysis should be done with the constant self-reminder that the parts belong to a
                whole. This recalls Hegel’s (1807/2005) ideal view of scientific development as the cycle
                of first breaking down concepts into ever-smaller categories, and then putting them
                back together to gain a holistic understanding.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
                This vision notwithstanding, sometimes analysis loses the forest for the trees. We use
                the term holistic analysis to serve as a reminder that all parts that are analysed should be
                considered not only in and of themselves, but also in relation to each other as parts of an
                interconnected whole. Moreover, as will be seen further on, entities that may seem “whole”
                in themselves can, in turn, be seen as parts of progressively more complex wholes
            </paragraph>
        </section>
        
        <section heading="Act One: documental becoming">
            <paragraph>
                A document is only truly a document when an information object is perceived by an
                agent in a particular context. With no agent, the “document” – what Couzinet (2015)
                called a “dormant document” – is merely an information object. In the most typical case
                of a document, the information object is a physical object, and the agent is a human
                being. Thus, in this paper we use “person” and “object” as a kind of shorthand, not
                denying that other types of documents exist (e.g. animal-object, person-person).
            </paragraph>
            
            <paragraph>
                When the person and the object come together (in present reality, in memory, or in
                imagination), a transaction occurs (Wood and Latham, 2014). This transaction entails the
                momentary <bold>“fusion” </bold> of two whole beings: the person and the object. Thus, in this
                framework, the object of analysis is always person plus object. The documental
                transaction has been viewed as the individual’s “experience” of the document (Latham,
                2014). The term experience here is drawn from Dewey’s (1934/2005) aesthetics. For
                Dewey, “an experience” is singular and meaningful, marked off from the banal procession
                of everyday experience. Dewey used the term transaction to describe such marked
                experiences; we extend the use of this term to characterize the coming together of person
                and object in all documents. Latham (2014) offered a framework for dissecting document
                experiences, in the form of a continuum of possible experiences with a document that
                range from efferent (cognitive, logical, intellectual) on one end and aesthetic (emotional,
                spiritual, holistic) on the other end. Here we add further nuance to that characterization
            </paragraph>
        </section>
            
        <section heading="Making meaning from information">
            <paragraph>
                <italic>
                    Buckland (1997) described documents as being made from the human processing of
                    objects. The first part of this processing is the ascertaining of information through the
                    senses and memory, as described above. Immediately and simultaneously, this
                    ascertaining gives way to meaning-making: the construction of meaning from information.
                </italic>
            </paragraph>
           </section>  
    </sections>
    
    <references>
        <reference>
            <authors>
                <author>
                    <first-name>Anderson</first-name>
                    <last-name> R.L. </last-name>
                </author>
            </authors>
            <year>2007</year>
            <paper-name>The functional ontology of filmic documents</paper-name>
            <journal>
                A Document (Re)turn:Contributions from a Research Field in Transition
            </journal>
        </reference>
        
        <reference>
            <authors>
                <author>
                    <first-name>Bates  </first-name>
                    <last-name> M.J. </last-name>
                </author>
            </authors>
            <year>2006</year>
            <paper-name>Fundamental forms of information</paper-name>
            <journal>
                Journal of the American Society for Information Science
            </journal>
        </reference>
        
    </references>
</scientific-paper>
